Things off here.
And, Devon, I believe you are first.
Great. Thank you so much.
My name is Devon Higgins.
I'm coming to you from Michigan,
where the.
The smokes have finally cleared.
But it is like a super dreary
Saturday morning,
so I appreciate you all being with me here
today.
I will just start sharing my screen.
Yes. And
slideshow.
Okay,
so yeah, I'm coming to you from Michigan.
I work at Michigan State University
where I'm a librarian,
so I'm typically working on building
digital collections
and supporting more analytical,
natural language based methods
in a variety of research projects
at the university.
But ever since I started
coding in graduate school,
my impulse has been to manipulate,
transform,
and estrange texts
in ways inspired by my long interest
in things like Po
and other constraint
based and experimental writing systems.
So over the last year,
I've been working on a site
that can take an initial text
and transform
it according to several methods
that I've set up so far that
that I'll talk you through.
The basic
process is you select a text,
then select a method.
And let me actually put this.
Whoops.
Put the link in the chat
so you're free to play around with it.
Where is the chat
okay there we go.
Yeah.
So the basic process is there's
some text here that you can select from.
And then a variety of methods
I'll talk about.
But basically once you select a text
then you have a sort of source text
and a result output.
So if you do something like an
plus x here, it allows you to scroll
through and get different
transformed values for the text.
And like I said,
I'll talk about these methods a bit more,
but you can feel free to try these out.
The only one I
will caution you about is the
the one called
Mood Shift here,
which makes use of vector models
and at the moment is running quite slow.
And so what you do with this though
is select.
You know, some words here.
And then you can select the model
you want to use
and a particular mood
that you want to apply.
And then kick it off
and it will take a minute.
So I'm going to go back in and talk
a little bit more about this here.
Okay.
Yeah.
So the first method I will talk about
is n plus seven.
I'm not sure how many of you
might be familiar with that,
but it's kind of a famous early
method of lipo,
and it operates by replacing the nouns
in a given text with an entry seven words
further down in the dictionary.
I initially thought implementing
something like this
with a computer
would be totally straightforward,
but once I work on the project,
I realized there are certain subtleties
at play that typically, or in fact,
must leverage human intervention.
The first thing, of course, is just the
selection of the dictionary that you use.
I wound up using something, wanting to use
something pretty comprehensive
after experimenting
with like smaller word lists.
So that source turned out to be wicked,
which is a huge,
you know, collection
user contributed language.
And the benefits of that are,
of course, that it's like comprehensive.
And I did whittle it down a bit,
eliminating some like
jargon in archaic terms
because it was just producing
too many words
that I didn't know what they meant.
Also, the other sort of human element
I realized in n
seven is making sure the words
fit grammatically into the sentence,
and so which provides the ability
to look up a word, return
the correctly inflected form of that word
so that you can balance
the surprising strangeness of whatever
this new word is
with a relatively balanced
syntactical appropriateness.
But as you can
probably see just from this example here,
the fitness of a word does go
a lot further than just matching
the grammatical inflection.
So I wanted to add flexibility to the
interface as well, allowing users
to select parts of speech other than noun
into replace selected words from seven
places back to seven places forward.
And I think the surprise and inspiration
that I found in the results
is the main point of this for me.
Not necessarily
the creation of a new work.
Rather, the goal is what I think it was.
Donald Barthelme called something
like basic language research
that is putting together unexpected words
and seeing what creates a spark or hits
some kind of nerve.
The corpus I've made available
so far is fairly haphazard.
It's poems.
I like, poems that were online, texts
I happen to have on my computer, or
ones that I thought could produce humorous
results, given a certain inevitable
that happens when
high seriousness
is punctured by random rewording.
So I also thought a form
like the sestina here
visible in Elizabeth Bishop's
poem, is nicely ripe
for this kind of method, given that
the repeating end words of the sestina
sort of compound,
the effect of the newness and strangeness
of the of the replacements.
So the gears of the N plus seven machine
kind of work in tandem
with the sestina machine.
I. Okay. Yeah.
The next.
So moving on from impulsive
and the next algorithmic transformation,
I was interested in applying again,
that seemed quite straightforward.
Was based on a Jackson McCloud
poem called Call Me Ishmael.
And this is again
a poem constructed according
to quite a routine mechanical method.
But in this case as well,
there is a bit of human intervention,
if not quite human ingenuity
at work in the writing itself,
in addition to the concept.
So, as you may be able to tell,
the poem is an acrostic, basically,
wherein the first letters of each word
and each line of each
stanza spell the famous
opening words of Moby-Dick.
So obviously, you know,
you have call me Ishmael here,
and that's repeated in each stanza.
And the words themselves are drawn
from the words of Moby Dick
as they appear in that text.
So it's a very mechanical process
based on the opening words of the text.
It was only on checking.
So I created, you know, a version of this
that you can also run
on Moby Dick,
as well as these other texts.
It was only upon
checking the original poem again
that I realized that I had misremembered
some of the details, and so my result
on the right differs to some extent
from MacLehose published work.
But I will also say that again,
another case where we're human
work comes into play.
I think MacLeod did not
necessarily follow it
with the most computerized strictness,
the rules of his implied method here.
So there is a little bit of work
on his end to fix it up a little.
Whereas mine, I'm just giving you the raw,
the raw poem here
according to the method,
as best as I could interpret it.
Okay.
And so like I said, you can also apply
this then on all kinds of other poems.
One example being here arena Rainer
Maria Rilke poem.
And I find the results
fascinating when applied to other poems.
I'd been kind of wondering
if there was something special about Moby
Dick in the words that it used there.
I mean, certainly
the brevity of the opening line helps
make it fit for this type of routine,
and also the vocabulary sort of special
in that first chapter of Moby
Dick called looming.
But I did like things and always
find little bits of poetry
that did spark something for me,
like in this case, Legendary eyes.
Gay's eyes, not dazzle or ripening yet
like,
seems a bit of a profound moment there.
I also,
you know, I'm a big fan of John Ashbery,
and I noticed Ashbery
kind of doesn't change that much
when you apply it to this method in a way.
And I kind of enjoyed
that this Ashbery version
still reads
kind of like Ashbery with this one.
I really think if you add
some creative punctuation,
it turns into something quite lovely.
With the hope excelled immense morning,
many exchanges,
night sidewalks, enjoyment,
head out paper effort, trailing hope.
I also like that
it wound up ending with the words
pausing effort,
which sounds like kind of a meta comment
on what the poem is doing
that is ending right there.
Some other examples where
I thought it was fun to change the word
a little bit.
That is the source of the acrostic,
not necessarily always the opening line,
but using a flood with
and producing
some interesting lines there.
The last
algorithm that I want to talk about
is a little bit different.
Over the course
of working on this project,
I had a lot of different sort of feelings
about algorithmic text creation.
Of course, at this time, at this moment,
with the
with AI having in some cases
the effect of inspiring people
to be more interested
in what is distinctly human.
And in other cases,
of course,
what I'm seeing in this conference
is a lot of inspiration of how to use AI
in creative and interesting ways.
But also there is the sense that to me,
some of some of the AI generated stuff
is producing a desire for the opposite,
a return
to something more human centered.
But on reflection, I really like that
these, these sort of brute
methods I've been talking about,
they're more or less kind of surprising.
They give you a surprising escape
from what I feel like is the bland,
kind of mind
numbing logarithm of the chat bot.
The chatbot whose utterances are,
of course,
honed in statistical precision
to produce the most expected tropes.
Otherwise, the random incursion of non
smooth language is refreshing to
in its own way.
And I think those sorts of surprising
bits of text
that can be kind of noisy and abrupt
help us break out
of what's mentioned in this code,
this code, this quote,
as producing objects for the subject
instead of a system that produces subjects
for the object in this quote.
Surprising was from 1989,
and it had to do with already
the media landscape sort of producing.
Taking over
languages, language in certain ways
and making it seem, in some cases,
as if our use of language is predetermined
according to set tropes.
So then, yeah,
the last method I'm want to talk about
today
is using word vector models.
And I'm not sure how familiar
everyone is necessarily with those, but
they're basically a mapping of words
from text in space
and usually something like 300 dimensions.
So a word is turned
into a vector of 300 numbers
and then can be treated mathematically.
And so what I thought
was interesting about
that was the potential to use that model,
not just to find similar words,
which is often what it's used for,
but to create vectors of emotional valence
that then could be used to change
the initial word in certain key ways.
There's an example I have on this slide.
And you can see that it
kind of works in some ways.
Certainly, you know, if you're looking
to move toward more ecstatic language,
then you get things like a maze
a lot and vision becomes visionary.
Upward becomes skyward,
but also excess becomes a mount,
which I'm not sure really does
much that we would have expected.
Another thing to do,
another one of the emotional vectors
I tried was anger, partially
because I was thinking
the more extreme emotions
would make this work a little bit better,
and so in this case, I dream enough,
I dream excess becomes I piss enough.
And it's surprising how much the word piss
and this into this.
When you start trying to use angry
languages, it's just apparently
a word that is very angry.
And the corpus
that these models were trained on.
So yeah.
And going back to this. Oh, interesting.
I've got a little bit of an error
in the title up here, but,
this is, you know,
John Don's poem becoming more angry,
increasingly say, my hate to be so furious
as I thought it was because it got
subject vicissitudes and you can sort of
see what it's doing there.
One of the problems that I've run into
with these word vector models
is that sometimes they
just get so lost in being angry
that they lose
the original sense of the word that it's
creating a replacement for which the goal
was to create sort of synonymous texts.
So yeah, I hope you find something to play
with that's of interest
here I was I can show more examples
if that's helpful.
And I would also
love to hear from anyone who's interested.
If anyone has ideas for vectors, I'm
sorry of models
or methods
they'd be interested in applying.
It would be great to collaborate
and this is a new project.
I expect to add more,
so I'll keep you posted.
Thanks very much.
Thank you.
Devon. Impressive.